Fairfield (Area) Church Papers, 1782-2000 Ms B33
Fairfield Museum and History Center
Fairfield (Area) Church Papers, 1782-2000
Ms B33
Fairfield Museum and History Center
10.25 Linear feet 27 boxes
Various materials from areas churches are gathered in this collection including legal documents, financial records, member lists, bulletins, newsletters, correspondence, calendars and meeting minutes.
Collection includes original records, photocopies, microfilm, photographs, slides and images on CD's.
Biographical/Historical note
The approximate dates of the establishment of the following churches are: Greenfield Hill-1725, Fairfield First Church Congregational-1640, Fairfield St. Paul's Episcopal-1850, Green's Farms Congregational Church-1611, Southport Congregational Church-1834, Southport Episcopal Methodist Church-1845, Southport Trinity Episcopal Church-1729, Stratfield Baptist Church-1751 (now known as First Baptist Church of Fairfield).
Conditions Governing Access note
There are no restrictions on access to this collection.
First Baptist Church of Fairfield. Stratfield Baptist Church.; First Church (Fairfield, Conn.). First Church Congregational.; Green's Farms Congregational Church (Westport, Conn.).; Greenfield Hill Church (Greenfield Hill, Fairfield, Conn.) .; Methodist Episcopal Church of Southport.; Southport Congregational Church (Southport, CT).; St. Paul's Episcopal Church (Fairfield, CT).; Trinity Episcopal Church (Southport, Conn.). Southport Trinity Church.; Bible records.; Churches--Connecticut.; Fairfield(Conn.); Southport(Conn.); Westport(Conn.)
- Fairfield Church surveys, 1963 & 1988, Box I; 250 items
  General note
  Disc included with printout
- Black Rock Congregational Church, Fairfield, 1898-1948, Box II; 100 items
- First Congregational Church Fairfield, church minutes, 1928-1960, Box III; 400 items
- First Church Congregational Fairfield, leaflets & manuals, 1850-1920, Box IV; 200 items
- First Church Congregational Fairfield, leaflets & manuals, 1850-1920, Box V; 200 items
- First Church Congregational Fairfield, leaflets & manuals, 1859-1920, Bov VI; 200 items
- First Church Congregational Fairfield, leaflets & manuals, 1880's-1980, Box VII; 200 items
- First Church Congregational Fairfield, First Church Herald, 1958-1971, Bov VIII; 200 items
- First Church Congregational Fairfield, Misc., Box IX; 200 items
- Greenfield Hill Congregational Church, minute books, 1943-1953, 1960-1969, Box X; 100 items
- Greenfield Hill Congregational Church, church calendars, 1931-1938, Box XI; 400 items
- Church calendars and sermons, Box XII
  - Greenfield Hill Congregational Church, church calendars, 1940-1947, 400 items
  - Sermons of Rev. George Wallace Banks, 1866-1896; 40 items
- Greenfield Hill Congregational Church, Ladies Organizations, 1887-1931, Box XIII; 6 items
- Greenfield Hill Congregational Church, George Merwin's research papers, Box XIV; 60 items
- Greenfield Hill Congregational Church-- Christian Endeavor, Hill Church News, reports & misc. papers, 1870-1967, Box XV; 120 items
- Greenfield Hill Congregational Church, misc. papers, Box XVI; 100 items
  - Legal documents, Folder 1
  - Financial records, 1811; 1868-1951; Folders 2-3
  - Subscription lists, 1845-1913; Folder 4
  - Meeting notice, 1841; minutes, n.d., Folder 5
  - Correspondence, 1868-1880; Folder 6
  - Building records, n.d.; Folder 7
  - Member lists, 1912, 1924; Folder 8
  - Greenfield Hill Bible Society records, 1844-1906; Folder 9
  - Christian Endeavor Society records, 1885-1899; Folders 10-11
  - Sunday bulletins, 1925, 1945-1946, 1958-1972; Folder 12
  - Newsletter, n.d., 1952; Folder 13
  - Sunday School publications, 1886, n.d.; Folder 14
  - Special programs, 1891-1944; Folder 15
  - Notices to members, 1952, 1962; Folder 16
  - History essays and pamphlets, Folder 17
  - Religious, daily and financial diary from anonymous, 1858-1859; Folder 18
- Greenfield Hill Congregational Church, misc. papers, Box XVII; 120 items
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1921; Folder 1
  - Church manuals, 1870 on; Folder 2
  - Annual meeting minutes, 1928; Folder 3
  - Annual meeting minutes, 1928; Folder 3
  - Financial records, 1902-1968; Folder 4
  - Church school flyers, Folder 5
  - Newsletter, 1968; Folder 6
  - Women's Guild brochure, 1968; Folder 7
  - Samples of cards given to shut-ins, Folder 8
  - Steeple fund appeal, 1944; Folder 9
  - Anniversary programs, 1876-1927; Folder 10
  - Special programs, 1887-1969; Folder 11
  - Historical and informational pamphlets, Folder 12
  - Photographs and slides, Folder 13
  - Newspaper articles, Folder 14
- Green's Farms Church of Christ correspondence & misc. items, 1836-1918; Box XVIII; 70 items
  Other Finding Aids note
  A detailed list of items in this box is available with the collection.
- Green's Farms Congregational Society Papers, Box XIX; 44 items
  - History, commemoration of British raid, 1979; Folder A; 30 items
  - Church pamphlets, Folder B; 8 items
  - Transcriptions, misc., Folder C; 4 items
  - Record book [Vol. II], 1728 Dec 12-1819 May 4; Folder D; 1 item
  - Record book [Vol. III] & Society Enrollment, 1820 May 6-1874 Jan 6, 1850 & 1832; Folder E; 1 item
- Green's Farms Congregational Society Papers, Box XX; 4 items
  - Record book [Vol. IV] & Roll of members, 1876 Jun 4-1927 Jan 7, 1909 & 1878; Folder A; 1 item
  - Record book [Vol. V] Treasurer's book, 1773-1831; Folder B; 1 item
  - Record book [Vol. VI] Fund agent's book, 1812-1932; Folder C
  - Greens Farms Society School records, 1785-1885; Folder D; 1 item
- Saint Paul's Church, Fairfield; Southport Methodist Episcopal Church; Southport Congregational Church, Box XXI; 100 items
- Southport Congregational Church School, 1835-1886; Box XXII; 158 items
  Custodial History note
  The items in this box were given by Royal Everts and contain papers from Levi Franklin Sherwood of Spruce Street, Southport, who was the Sunday School Superintendent of the Southport Congregational Church.
  - Sunday School attendance books, 1875-1877, 1880, 1885-1886; Folder A; 111 items
  - Sunday School collection envelopes, Folder B; 36 items
  - Books, Folder C; 3 items
    - Sunday School Register, 1875
    - YMCA Hymn and Tune book
    - Classbook inscribed "Miss Annamelia Sherwood", 1835
  - Periodicals, Folder D; 8 items
    - Scholar's Quarterly, 1st and 2nd quarters, 1880
    - Christian World, April 1880
    - Handful of Pleasant Delights, 1879
    - Little Wanderer's Friend (annual), July 1879
    - American Missionary, August 1878
    - Good Company, vol. 6, no. 1, August 1878
- Trinity Episcopal Church, Southport, newsletters and misc. papers, 1851-1962; Box XXIII; 80 items
  Related Archival Materials note
  See also MS B43
- Miscellaneous, Box XXIV; 25 items
  - Pamphlets--various churches in Connecticut
  - Rate book for the Episcopal Society, Stratfield, 1785
- Southport Congregational Church Microfilms, 1843-1971; Box XXV
  Immediate Source of Acquisition note
  Materials in this box from Accession number L94.Jul.13
  - Church records, history through annual reports, 1843-1858
  - Church Bulletins and Annual meeting 1843-1900; History through 1952
  - Church records 1898-1920; calendars to 1920
  - Church bulletins, The Messenger, 1960-1963
  - Church bulletins, Order of Worship, 1964-1967, 1968-1971
  - Church bulletins, Order of Worship, 1968-1971, 1945-1946
- Stratfield Baptist Church records, 1740's-2000's; Box XXVI; Images on 6 CD's
  Detailed list of images available in the box.
- Pages from record books of Fairfield area churches, Box XVII
  - Fairfield First Congregational Church council minutes and miscellaneous papers, 1639-1949; Folder A
  - Greens Farms Congregational Church burials, baptisms and communicants, 1725-1903; Folder B
  - Greenfield Hill Congregational Church baptisms, marriages, burials, memorabilia, 1805-1961; Folder C; Mostly photocopies of the original record book
  - St. Paul's Episcopal Church of Fairfield marriages, 1856-1870; Folder D; Typed copy